Okay, I'll wait a few seconds. People
are late.
We have barely
uh
75 people in class. Where are the rest?
So what do you mean by the website is
not working here in Kari?
What's the issue?
The meeting link was there. Okay, let me
post the uh meeting link. Uh TAS, can
you please post the meeting link on
Piaza?
Could you please do that immediately?
Uh and Bruno, just let the folks in uh
uh Kegali know that the meeting link is
on Piaza. Okay, let me begin. So good
morning everybody.
The uh this is the last in our series of
lectures on convolutional neural
networks.
We're going to start again with a quick
recap of back propagation through a CNN
and then we'll look at some additional
back propagation rules that were not
covered in the last class. We'll look at
some modifications, transposition,
scaling, rotation, deformation, and
variance. Invariance to other kinds of
operations besides shift. We'll look at
segmentation and localization and a
little bit of the history of
convolutional neural networks which
hopefully will give us time to briefly
mention a couple of very popular
architectures resonance and densets.
So here is the story that we have so
far. Shift invariant pattern
classification tasks such as does this
picture contain a cat or does this
recording include the word hello are
best performed by scanning for the
target pattern using CNN or time delay
neural networks. Now these are shared
parameter models because scanning with a
model is the same as having a very large
model where many with many sub networks
which are all identical and these can be
trained using variations of back
propagation that account for this shared
parameter structure.
So when you train a CNN of this kind, a
CNN typically has several convolutional
and pooling layers. The output of the
final of these layers is typically
flattened and passed through an MLP or
maybe just a simple soft.
And so when you want to train the
network for training the convolution and
pooling layers, uh you pass each
training instance through the net, you
compute a divergence between the output
of the net and the desired output of the
network and then back propagate
derivatives going backwards through the
network. We have regular back
propagation rules through the final NLP.
The uh derivatives at the input to this
NLP can be folded back into the maps
into the same shapes as the maps that
were unrolled to provide and flattened
to provide the input to the MLP. So now
we have derivatives divergence
derivatives for every element for of
every one of the maps in the final
layer. those derivatives can be further
back propagated through the rest of the
network and that's where we need
adjustments.
So the adjustments we need we saw were
for both convolutional layers and
pooling layers. For convolutional layers
given the derivatives for the output
activation maps in any layer we had to
figure out how to compute the
derivatives with respect to the aphine
maps
on which the activation was applied to
get the activation map. Subsequently, we
had to figure out how to compute the
derivatives for the output of the
previous layer from which these hyphen
maps were computed and also for the
filters that were used to compute these
maps. For the pooling layers given the
derivatives with respect to the output
of the pooling layer, we had to figure
out how to compute the derivative with
respect to the input of the layer.
So convolution layers first how do you
compute derivatives for the aphine maps
from the derivatives for the activation
map. We saw this the convolution
operation gives us many aphine maps one
per filter. Then we apply an activation
function element wise to get the final
activation maps. During backdrop, you
expect that you will have the
derivatives for every element of every
one of these activation maps. To
propagate those derivatives backward to
obtain derivatives for these aine maps,
we used a simple chain rule. So what was
the chain rule? Anybody remember? How
did we get this derivative from these
guys
from the elements over here? How did we
do that? Anybody
remember this?
Come on guys, this was easy. Specific
chain rule we used,
right? Derivative of the activation
times the Exactly. So this was just this
very simple operation here. uh you
multiplied the derivative with respect
to the activation element by the
derivative of the activation function
itself to get the derivatives for the
aphine every element of every aphine
map. Easy.
So the next question was how do you get
the derivatives for again you have the
uh
input
channels to a convolution and then we
had a filter and this filter gave us a
single output alphine map. And so the
question was given the derivatives for
all the elements of this aphine map how
did we compute the derivatives going
backwards
for all of these input channels and for
the filter. So does anybody remember how
we did that?
How did we do this guys?
If if you were in the last class you
might have seen some flashing pictures.
So what was the process roughly
speaking? Anyone
do you remember how we did this?
Come on guys, we were there in the
class, right? So how did we do that?
Wait a few seconds. We redid the
convolutions. What did we convolve for
the input? Pad the der derivative map
and convolve with flipped weights. So
and uh for the filters, what did we do?
we mana
what did we do for the filters
do you remember
for the filters convolve the input and
dl over dz fantastic right so that's all
we did if you want the derivatives for
the by the input channels the derivative
for any specific input channel was
obtained by using the by pulling out the
the corresponding channels of all the
filters and then so these are the
channels of all the filters. We flipped
these channels left to right, top to
bottom. And and
then we
zero padded
these guys, all of these guys, right?
And then we convolved the zeropadded
output derivative maps, a derivative
maps with this transposed filter, left
flipped filter, right? And that gave us
the derivative for the input channel. So
everybody remember this?
Does everyone remember this? Yes or no?
This is easy, right? Nothing complex.
And how did we compute the derivatives
for the filter?
So if this was an aphine map obtained by
using this filter against all of these
input channels then
we going backwards we would have
obtained the derivatives for all the
elements of this aine map. We simply
convolved this derivative map with all
of these input channels to get the
derivatives for all the elements of all
the channels of the filter that was used
to compute this aine map. Does everyone
remember this?
Yes or no?
Right. So,
okay, I have a few thumbs up. I'll just
go with that.
And so we've seen how to compute
derivatives for these Z's, for the
filters, and for the input channels in
the convolution layer. The other one was
for the pooling layer. How did we
compute how how do we compute
derivatives for the pooling layer. Now,
and the pooling layer, if you're
performing max pooling, pooling
basically groups pools groups of values
to reduce jitter sensitivity. And so you
have a pooling pooling filter which
performs this uh grouping operation and
you scan the input with this pooling
filter. The most common pooling is max
pooling which picks the largest element
for of every window that it's
considering at every position. So if
this were the window uh again we want
what I mean by jitter sensit
sensitivity. said that if you're looking
for something like a flower, you can't
get too specific that the petal must be
uh let me change the color, right? You
can't get too specific and say that the
petal must be exactly here and this guy
must be exactly here and this guy must
be exactly here for this to be a a a
desired uh feature. If this thing moves
left or right by a little bit, it still
is the same feature. And so the way we
got that was through this polling filter
which looked at a little window over
which this kind of jitter was considered
permissible and we picked the largest or
the average or some other operation on
all of these to achieve that jitter
sensitivity. That answer your question,
right? And so when you perform max
pooling,
you'd be looking at a windows like this
one and just pick the largest value. But
the actual operation you performed was
to first identify the location of the
max and then copy that element over. So
we just do that at every position
through the input when we were going
backwards. Now back propagation would
give you the derivative for this
element. This element was obtained from
this window. But specifically this
element was cop copied only the largest
value over. So we know that the rest of
them did not influence this element at
all. So they get zero derivatives and
the derivative over here just gets
copied going back into this position. So
everybody remember this one?
Does everyone remember this?
Yes. No. Okay. like 10 as I'm not too
ambitious today. And so this was what uh
the forward pass of max pooling was. You
scan the input with a small window.
Within each window, you pick the
position of the largest value and then
you copied the
input value at this position to the
output.
When you're going backwards, you have
the location of the largest value. So
you just copy the derivative over to the
position of from which it was obtained
the plus equals. Why did we have the
plus equals again over here instead of
just an equals? Why do we have the plus
equals?
Anybody?
Why do we have this here?
Come on. You answered me two days ago.
So
Mac, that's the overlap. the same
adjacent windows could pull the same
large value. Now, this it turns out is
kind of an interesting thing. If you
look at older uh
uh versions of PyTorch, it didn't use
plus equals, it just used equals. That
was a bug. And so, more recently, they
fixed it and now they actually have plus
equals I believe in the backdrop for max
pool. Right? It doesn't really matter if
adjacent windows don't overlap, but if
they do it matters.
And then for mean pulling, we did the
same thing except that we computed the
mean of all of these values and copied
it over. So when you go back, the
derivative at the location that this
mean was copied into is now uniformly
distributed over all the locations that
contributed to it. So if if it were
considering if it came from a 2 +2
window, every element was multiplied by
1 over4 and then added up to give you
this guy. That's the mean, right? So the
derivative was distributed in four equal
four equal parts over all of these four
entries. In general, if the window is
size k + k, then the derivative is
distributed over all 1 / k equally over
all 1 / k^ 2 elements. And so here is
the pseudo code for mean pulling. Going
forward, you pick the mean value within
each window. going backwards,
you just you already have the derivative
out here that gets copied after being
weighted over by 1 / k² over all of
those positions. And again, this plus
equals accounts for the fact that
adjacent windows might overlap. So, is
all of this clear to you guys?
Everything that we've done so far,
right? So what will be the effect? If
you don't have a plus equals Bruno, then
the derivative is going to be wrong. As
you scan, you're just going to get the
derivative from the latest window that
contributed to it. So you're going
you're always going to have a derivative
that's going to be off by a bit. That
answer your question, Bruno?
Okay. And so we've got both of these.
And that leads us to our first poll
because that is the end of our revision
section and we go on to newer topics.
So
uh Nelia if you have ties then both
elements
when perturbed will affect the output.
So both of them will have uh the uh
derivative can will get copied to both
elements.
Yes, very in in uh the in most cases
when you have max pooling the uh pooling
is done so that you don't have overlap.
Not always but in all the earlier models
that's how it was right.
So if you're back dropping to the first
index if there's no overlap that should
be fine. If there is an overlap there,
that's what that's about. Right? So,
uh
I'm going to stop this poll.
Can anybody answer this first question?
True or false?
True. Second one, true or false?
True. Okay. So when back propagating
through a max pooling layer, derivatives
from the cooling output back propagate
only to the position of the largest
input within the input window cooling
window for that output. When back
propagating through a mean cooling
layer, derivatives are distributed
uniformly over the entire pooling window
for that output.
So that's everything we've done so far.
But then we had something else that we
didn't consider in the last class.
Resampling layers, upsampling and down
sampling sampling layers can increase or
decrease the size of the map. Right? So
up sampling followed by convolution we
saw can be viewed as convolution with a
fractional stride. Convolution or
pulling followed by down sampling can be
viewed as convolution or pulling with a
stride greater than one. So how do we
back propagate upsampling and down
sampling pairs?
First, what is the downsampling layer?
In the down sampling layer, if we wanted
to downsample by a factor of S, then we
basically shaded out discarded
S minus one of every S rows and S - one
rows of every S columns. So all of these
guys shaded in black. They were ignored.
Effectively, they were masked out and
the rest of the elements were copied to
the output. So my question to you is
this. If this is what I'm doing, then
does this element here contribute
anything to the output?
Does this element okay so what would the
derivative of the loss with respect to
this element be?
Zero. Right?
So very easy. Back back now going back
again. Does this element contribute to
the output? Yes or no?
What is the derivative of the loss with
respect to this element?
What is it?
One,
it's going to be the same as the loss
derivative over here, right? Because
this element just got copied to the
output, right?
Yes or no?
And so the derivative over here is just
going to get copied into this location.
That make sense to everybody,
right? So but for this there's a simple
rule. The rule is if I have some process
and the input is some size
and then this process gives you some
output from which I compute a scalar
loss. The gradient of this loss with
respect to the input of this process is
going to be exactly the same size as the
input itself.
That rule making sense to all of you
guys. If the you have these many
elements being involved in computing
this loss, then every element over here
this loss has a derivative with respect
to every one of these elements. So the
derivative must the gradient not the
derivative but the gradient which is the
transpose must be the same size as the
input itself.
That make sense to everybody?
Right? And so here's what we would do.
We know that the in derivative of the
input to the downsampling layer should
be the same size as the input itself. So
the first thing we do is to allocate an
a a map of the size of the input that
went into down sampling. Subsequently we
know you know we know all the elements
that were masked out when the
downsampling happened. So their
derivatives as we all saw already saw
are just going to be zero. Right? And
now just the remaining elements those
were the ones that were copied over. And
because they were copied over, these
guys basically came here as is. And so
the derivatives here are going to go
back. Whatever perturbation of this guy
changes the loss by that's exactly how
much perturbation of this guy is going
to change the loss by. So the derivative
over here simply gets copied over. Is
this process for the down derivative of
downsampling making sense?
Yes. Okay. What does this process look
like?
What does the process look like going
backwards?
Anyone?
It's just upsampling, right? The
derivative of downsampling is repeat
after me. What's the derivative of
downsampling,
guys?
Upsampling, right?
I mean it's not exactly upsampling
because there's some issues with the
boundaries but if you ignore what's
happening at the boundaries it's
upsampling. Okay. Now
I have pseudo code for I'll skip it.
Right. What about the upsampling layer?
In the upsampling layer we introduced
sus one rows and sus1 columns of zeros
between
adjacent elements. Right. Okay. So Bruno
you say not exactly. Why? Why is it not
exactly? Can you tell me? You're right,
but can you tell me why it's not exactly
h
for this guy?
Not very clear to me. So here, see this
final column? If I'm upsampling from
here going back, I have no idea that I
should be adding this final column or
this final row because whether I down
sample this one
or whether I downsampled this larger
one, let me clear this picture. So if I
downsample
this guy, which is just these,
the output is going to be exactly the
same as if I down sampled this guy,
right?
Yes or no?
Yes or no? Right? Yes. And so there's
this fuzziness about the boundary.
This other than the fuzziness about the
boundary, it's exactly an upsampling
layer. And so this fuzziness of the
about the boundary is resolved by
keeping track of the size of the input
to the downsampling layer. That's all
that that clarify guys,
right? So that would have to be you
you'd always start from the top left. So
that's always a convention. Okay.
All right.
Now
what about upsampling?
In upsampling you're introducing S minus
one rows and S minus one uh rows and S -
one columns of zeros between actually
adjacent rows and columns. So this is
what happens right now tell me this when
I'm going backwards back propagation is
going to give me some derivative for
this element. Right?
Is there any element over here
which when perturbed will change this
guy?
Is there any element of the input that
would have changed this element?
No. Right? These are just zeros that
were arbitrarily introduced without
referring to the rest of the inputs. So
which means that this derivative is
really not influenced by any element
over here. This is not contributing
going backwards.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right? And so
when I back propagate again the same
rule, right? The derivative of the input
to the upsampling layer, the gradient of
the input to the upsampling layer must
have the same size as the input itself.
So mate was if you're using
interpolation going forward then you'd
have to worry about things but in
upsampling you don't you just stick
zeros you expect the convolution to take
care of the the learned convolution to
take care of the interpolation
that answer right okay so
here when I'm going backwards I expect
the derivative to be the same size as
this guy but I know all of these
elements really have no
compl no counterpart in the input they
were just zeros that were introduced
when you're going forward. Right? So
during backdrop, these guys do not
influence the derivatives going
backwards. Right? But what about this
guy?
What about this guy? What can we say
about its derivative going back? Anyone?
One.
So this derivative, okay,
this element is the same as this
element. Correct? Yes or no?
Right.
So, what is this derivative?
What is this derivative?
It's going to be just copied over from
here.
Make sense to everybody,
right? And so, we just copy those
derivatives over. What does this
operation look like?
What does this operation look like? Down
sampling, right? So the derivative of
upsampling is a down sampling process.
The derivative of downsampling is an
upsampling process. The only fuzziness
is about the boundaries. If you keep
track of the sizes of the inputs going
forward, you always know how to deal
with the boundaries. Okay? And so
writing code for back propagating
through down sampling or upsampling is
really really simple, right? You're
literally just copying things over in
the right locations.
Now
in reality, when you actually perform
down sampling after an operation, you
don't actually directly perform down
samp perform the full operation and then
perform down sampling. That would be a
lot of unnecessary computation. So what
you do is you just perform the
operation.
What is that?
These zeros
they are not they're only used further
downstream right iet
you introduce zeros you increase the
size of the input and then you they're
used further downstream correct yeah but
they have not come from anything over
here so these derivatives are simply
dropped
right
so because they really don't have
there's nothing you can perturve over
here that's going to change this zero
this zero was just zero stuck in which
means that uh there is no this
contributes nothing to the derivatives
out here.
That make sense to everybody?
I'm assuming so. Right. So
now
typically
you don't actually perform spec explicit
downsampling. You're going to perform
convolution or pooling with a stride.
And when you perform convolution or
pooling with a stride
then
uh this is effectively performing
convolution with down sampling. But
there is an annoying bit about it. If I
if I perform convolution with a stride
say doing this window and then stride by
two and then doing this window and so on
[snorts] and then you try to work out
the back propagation rules. the math
gets very ugly very quickly because you
have to deal with the business of the
stride.
So it's much much much simpler to
actually think of convolution with a
stride as convolution with a stride of
one followed by downsampling
because we know exactly how to
compute derivatives going backward
through this guy. That's just another
convolution operation. And we know
exactly how to compute derivatives
through this guy. That's just an
upsampling operation. So rather than
trying to compute derivatives directly
over here for convolution with a stride
of two, there is the realization that
it's a regular convolution with a stride
of one followed by down sampling. And so
back propagation is first going to back
propagate through the down sampling and
then through the convolution with the
stride of one. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. No. Rest of you guys. I'm seeing
like half a dozen yeses.
Okay. So,
like five yeses, man. Can I have 10
today? I was asking for 25 yesterday.
Was greeting.
All right. Okay.
All right. So,
this is what you'd want to do. First
back propagate through the downsampling
and then through the convolution with
the stride of what? Convolution with a
fractional stride. What exactly was
convolution with a fractional stride?
Anybody? What was that?
What was convolution with a fractional
stride?
Upsampling followed by convolution.
Correct?
So convolution when I say convolution
with a stride of 0.5
what you're really doing is upsampling
by a factor of two and then convolving
with a stride of one. This is the
equivalent of striding by half a pixel
at a time right
because the stride
whatever the stride is one over the
stride is the scale by which the output
is modified. If the stride is two the
output is going to shrink by a factor of
two. If the stride is 0.5, the output is
going to expand by a factor of two.
Right? So this is actually upsampling by
two followed by a stride of one.
Right?
This everybody good with this? Bruno
this this makes sense to you
since you had the question.
Okay. So what is the output
this guy? Let's say I have something of
this kind right if I stride by one
assuming I have zero padded for to keep
this maintain the output the output is
still going to be 2 + 2 correct Bruno
if I stride by one if I stride by two
what is the size of the output going to
be it's just going to be one pixel so it
has shrunk by a factor of two on every
side right
S.
So in general striding by S decreases
the size by by a factor S. Correct?
What if S is less than one? If S is.5,
it's going to modify the size of the
input by a factor
two. Right? So if the input is size n
and then if you stride by s the output
is size n / s correct yes or no
what if s is a fraction then what
happens
if s is 0.5 what happens it increases
right so that's what a fractional stride
means but then how exactly do you
implement it the way you implement it is
by upsampling by a factor 1 / s and then
striding by one.
That make sense to everybody?
Right? So that's what a fractional
convoling with a fractional stride is.
Bruno that answer your question.
Okay.
So when you encounter a convolutional
layer with a fractional stride, you must
realize that it's actually an upsampling
followed by regular convolution,
right? And uh then you can just back
propagation back propagate through the
standard convolution rule, you know,
derivative rules for the convolution
with stride one and the very simple
rules we saw for back propagating
through upsampling by two. So this makes
sense to everybody.
Okay. So mate was the boundaries you
have to keep size track of size sizes
that's all. So again pooling is
typically performed with strides greater
than one results in shrinking of the
map. Right? And so [clears throat] again
when you're pooling with a stride it's
convenient to think of it as pooling
with a stride one followed by
downsampling.
uh and uh same thing right so that's the
math but then it turns out as I was
saying yesterday
uh so Edward what is preferred over what
I'm not sure what what the two options
are in your mind can you clarify
you can't how do you how do you stride
by less than one when you're shifting
forward can you stride by 0.5 Five
I have a picture of this kind right I
have a number let's say
I have these guys these are my pixels
and then I'm convolving by a2 +2 filter
right
can this tried by less than one Edward
like less than one
it cannot this is the way you implement
it Right?
Because everything is integer.
That's why
so
even mathematically you basically uh
just upsample and convolve. Anyways, so
go back to our point that it's always
simpler when you look at it through
code. Suppose I have a simple operation,
right? function y equals
so you know I have some function which
says y= f ofx
let me erase this I'm writing some
crappy pseudo code but live with me
right function
and then within this code I have
z equals
and let me actually x and w all right z=
wx x
and y =
some sigma of z. Let's say if this is my
code right now I give you dl
over dy.
I want function
dl /
dx
comma dl / dw
equals whatever the derivative of dl /
dy.
What is this function going to look
like? Basically this computed y from x
and w. I want the reverse function which
computes the derivatives of a loss with
respect to x and w given the derivative
of the loss with respect to y. What
would this look like?
Is this problem statement making sense
to you guys what I just asked?
Maybe I can make it clearer. Right?
Let's say I'm given dl over dy and so I
want to
I I want a function f. This is a
function definition and the output of
the function is dl / dx
and dl / dw. Okay.
And I want this derivative function
whose input is dl / d bar.
What will this function look like? Can
anybody tell me just writing this code
from this code?
Anyone
with a quick look
here? So here's what happens. Y is a
function of Z, right? We have the
derivative for Y. So what is DL over DZ?
What is DL over DZ?
That's simply going to be dl dy
sigma prime correct yes or no
over here
now I have dl / dz right what is dl / dw
what is this
going to be D L / DZ * Z, right? W or is
it not? It's going to be DL / DZ *
YX,
sorry, X, right? And DL /
DX
is going to be DL / DZ * W, right?
This makes sense to everybody what I
just wrote.
So look what I did. I didn't even worry
about what the code was, right? I just
saw the Z equals WX Y= sigma of Z. So I
started from the bottom and computed the
derivative for Z. Then I just took a
step back and computed the derivative
for W and X. Right?
Yes. No. Did you guys understand this?
Right. It doesn't matter if this this
operation is in a loop for i equals you
know 1 to n whatever the same operation
holds and so here is what I would do if
I'm looking at what's happening inside a
convolution
I'm scanning the input
right then within each input I'm going
over all the filters
and I'm going to I'm initializing the
zvalue for the Z's, you know, going
forward, you're computing Z's, right?
And then you're computing Y's. Then
at each position, I'm going over the
filter, right?
And within the filter, I'm just adding
the W * the Y from the previous layer to
Z. So this operation finally gives me a
Z at every position. The Y itself is
just computed by applying an activation
to it. So this code making sense to
everybody know this making sense
what we just did right I'm going to use
exactly the same rules that I did
earlier okay I'm going to say if I want
to compute the derivatives say I have
the derivative for y how do I compute
the derivatives for z w and the y of the
previous layer I'm going to do the same
thing I'm going to first it's back
propagation. So the order of all of
these loops is going to be reversed.
Okay. Then just as I did in you know in
my example first I'm going to get the
derivative for Z from the derivative of
Y up here by multiplying the derivative
for the activation function. And then
within the innermost loop again Z is
obtained by multiplying W and Y. So the
derivative for y is the derivative for z
* w and the derivative for w is the
derivative for z * this making sense
what I just did
rest of you guys this making sense right
I'm using exactly the same code as here
with exactly the same indices I don't
change a single thing and so I don't
even have to think about it everything
will just work out because the
arithmetic makes sense
H is the height. W is the width event
you bet of the input.
This make sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Guys, this makes sense. Rest
of you guys, can I see some a dozen
thumbs ups, please?
7 8 Okay, I got 13. Good number. And so
that's all I need to do, right? I didn't
need to understand that things were
convolutions. I didn't need to
understand a single thing. I literally
just flip the code around. And this
works even if I'm convolving with a
stride. Going forward, I'll be doing
everything with a stride. Going
backward, I'm going to use the same
logic. All that I do is that uh I'm
going to be going backward. So this
should have really been over here. I'm
it doesn't matter whether I'm going
forward or backward. If I were doing
this right, the order of the indices uh
would be flipped and the rest of the
arithmetic is exactly the same. Where
are you seeing speaking of x minus this
is the position right? So when you're
scanning
you're going to
you you have you're scanning within this
window
to perform the integration starting from
this position.
So one of these is this position. The
other is the position within the window.
That make sense
when you're computing the Z, right?
Okay. So that's all it is, right?
And so here we are. We can do the same
thing, right? Pooling, you can do the
same thing. So pulling, [clears throat]
you can just flip things around and the
whole thing just works. Okay, I'll skip
this. So that goes to our second book.
The idea was I was trying to convey was
if you don't understand the math, you
can just look at the code and you can
always write code to compute derivatives
without knowing the first thing about
what the math is doing
simply by writing everything backwards.
It's amazing. You can use this logic to
compute derivatives of any function. It
doesn't matter how ugly the function is.
If you can write the function, write
code for the function, you can compute
derivatives for the function using the
same code running backwards.
Okay,
I'll give you five seconds.
I'll end the poll.
Anybody want to answer these questions?
True, true, false. True, true, true.
Three, two. Okay, let's see. Bruno was
right. Right. The backward pass of an
upsampling layer is downsampling. The
backward pass of a down sampling layer
is upsampling. You can't simply use an
upsampling layer as the backward pass of
down sampling and vice versa.
Right? Why is that? Why is the third one
false?
Anybody? Why is the third one false
guys? So those of you who answered
false, you got it right. You need to
account for the original shape of the
input because of the crazy craziness at
the boundaries. If you ignore the
boundaries, you could do so. or you have
to worry about the boundaries, right?
And so we've shown how to compute
derivatives for every bit of a of this
convolutional network regardless of
whether you have strides uh what have
you. Correct?
So is everybody comfortable that we've
done all of this so far? Yes or no?
Okay, fantastic. And so the story so far
is that the convolutional neural network
is a supervised version of a
computational model of mamalian vision.
It includes convolutional layers
comprising learned filters that scan the
outputs of the previous layer. Pooling
layers that operate over groups of
outputs from the convolution layer for
jitter and variance and resampling
layers that can increase or decrease the
spatial extent of the representation.
This these are often integrated with
preceding or succeeding operations to
convert them to operations with integer
or fractional strides. The parameters of
the network can be learned through
regular back propagation. Max pooling
layers must propagate derivatives only
over the maximum element for each pool.
Other pooling operators use regular
gradients or subgradients.
Derivatives must sum over appropriate
sets of elements to account for the fact
that the network is in fact a shared
parameter network. So
jitter invariance where
again uh
we went over this a little while ago. I
said that, you know, if you had a filter
that detected this feature, you still
wanted to say you had that this pattern
from a flower was seen even if this this
petal moved forward by half a pixel or
if this one moved forward moved left by
a pixel, right? And so you wanted
invariance or in the position of
invariance in the components that
composed the larger pattern and that
came through max pooling.
So
right CNN's are shift invariant
meaning we said where we uh exactly
right so we said we started off saying
we want the network to fire regardless
of the location of the flower. So we
created this entire theory and a lot of
uh pretty algorithms to to construct and
train networks that could detect for
instance that both of these pictures
have a flower. But what if we so these
are shift invariants but what if we have
want other kinds of invariants. What if
I want rotation invariants? I wanted to
detect the flower even if the flower is
rotated a little bit. I wanted to detect
a flower even if the flower has scaled
up or if it's reflected upside down. How
could I introduce these
invariances?
Any idea
how could we? Augmentation.
Augmentation is a good idea,
but
something more. Yeah, augmentation is
generally how we do it. But if you were
to do it theoretically correctly, how
would you do it
depth? Right? So here is what happened.
When I was detecting a flower, what was
it I actually did? I had a flower
pattern detector and I scanned the
input. And so the same flower pattern
detector was applied in both locations
in order for me to get position and
variance, right?
Yes or no?
Yes or no guys? Right. Okay. So
I can think of shift in variance from a
different perspective. I can write this
as
saying that when I'm scanning with a
filter instead I can say that I'm
actually scanning with two filters. One
is the original I'm I'm computing with
two filters. One is the original filter
and the other is a shifted version of
the same filter. Right? And that's going
to give me these two outputs. Yes or no?
Right? So I got shift invariance by
shifting the filter.
Yes or no?
Does that make sense to you guys? What
was scanning? It was just shifting the
filter. Right? I got shift in variance
by shifting the filter. How would I get
rotation in variance?
Using the same theory,
you'd allow the filter to rotate. How
would I get scaling in variance?
I'd allow the filter to scale. Right?
Very simple. The concept is so pretty.
And so
if I want to generalize shift invariant
in the original thing I said the Z at a
new position was a Y convolved by a
shifted version of the filter to
position I J. Right? If I want rotation
invariance I get a Z which convolves the
Y with a rotated version of the filter.
I can combine rotation and shift and say
rotate
and shift. And so I can now I'm going to
get rotation invariance for the same
feature. This make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Right. Beautiful. Right. So
there's a problem. Why don't we do this?
Why don't we do this?
It has to do with the fact that
you're going to have, you know, you can,
it's not just rotation. You can think of
every kind of transform that you want
invariance to. And so you're going to
transform this filter to explicitly make
copies of the filter with each
transformation applied to the filter.
And then you'd be scanning with all of
these transformed versions of the
filter, right?
This means we need the set of transforms
to be enumerated and discrete.
So I'd have a discrete because I'm
making copies of the filter, right? So I
need a discrete set of rotation,
scaling, reflections, etc. that I can
list out. And this filter is going to be
put through all of these guys. And the
code itself is you know here was your st
stand standard code you were scanning at
each position you pulled out a chunk of
the input you did a tensor product with
the filters and then applied an
activation here at each position you're
going to pull out a chunk of the input
but then the filter itself you have an
additional loop. These are all the
transforms that you're going to apply to
the filter. And so the chunk is going to
be convolved with with all the
transformed versions of the filter.
Which means the set of permitted
transforms has to be in this code. It
has to be enumerated.
And how many transforms can you get? If
I want rotation and variance, I have
rotation by 1°ree, rotation by 2°,
rotation by 3°, rotation by 270°. Right?
This is going to be an enormous number
and every one of them is going to create
an output map.
That make sense to every one of you
guys? Right?
So each one of these is going to create
a map. Right? And the whole thing is
just going to blow up. That's why we
don't do it. That's why we just simply
use augmentation. And 270 is a random
number I chose. You can, you know, you
can have any number of degrees, right?
So,
but it's exact unlike when you're using
augmentation because you do this when
you're back propagating. If you back
propagate through all of these variance
of the all the channels computed by all
the variance of the filter, you're going
to get the derivatives for all of these
variants of the filter. Those
derivatives can all be transformed back
and you're going to get the derivative
for the original base filter itself. And
that's what you would use. And the nice
thing about this is that it's not just
rotations. It's not just reflections.
It's not just any one of these. You can
have any kind of distortion, any kind of
transformation of the filters. And you
can make you can choose the kind of
distortions you want invariance to and
you can build your network or you can
transform your filters through those
distortions and make the network
invariant to it. Unfortunately, it's
computationally ridiculous and so we
never do it. We take the much simpler
method of simply augmenting our data.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. What we just said, right? But
the idea is beautiful, isn't it? Don't
you think? What do you think?
Right? If that made sense, give me a
yes. If you think the idea is beautiful,
give me some other.
Uh
all right anyways let me move on. Right.
So the story so far I can add this new
bullet. The models can be easily
modified to include invariance to other
transforms although these tend to be
computationally absurd.
Okay.
What are
uh what about the location?
We said we want to build a network that
will fire regardless of the location of
the flower.
But that we obtained by effectively
scanning for the flower. And so if it
fired at any location in the picture, it
means there was a flower. But then could
we not look at where it fired and also
detect where the flower occurred? What
do you guys think?
What do you guys think? Right, we were
scanning and if it fired at any
location, we said there was a flower.
But then you can say, hey, you know
what? It was high here and here. So, I
think the flowers are here and here. You
should be able to say that, right?
Yes. Yes. If we keep track, not quite
because once you begin distributing the
patterns, things get a little ugly. But
then there are many situations where we
really want to know where the pattern
was dis determined detected. So we know
that this guy actually carries
information about the location of the
flower somewhere in it. So what we what
is done when you're trying to find the
locations we try to detect bounding
boxes basically the box within which the
pattern has occurred. And now you have
what is called a multitask network which
generates two outputs. The first of
course is your regular class output. The
second is a network is a head which
gives you the coordinates of the
bounding box within which the object was
detected.
And now the network you're going to have
trained training data which not only
tells you where if there is a flower but
where the flower was. And the location
information and the training data is now
going to be used to train the second
head.
This make sense to everybody?
Yes. Now, yeah. And so
you can do this to detect other kinds of
things. You might have seen these
networks which draw skeletons of the
skull, right? The joints of a stick
model
that's uses the same technique. In fact,
if you had been in CMU 5 years ago, as
you walked down the corridor from uh uh
from the Gates building to the Hillman
building, there was a screen at the end
and Yasa Yaser Shik had put up this demo
which would draw the skeleton. It was
very scary of every person walking down
the corridor. So you could see your own
skeleton. He did that with a CNN which
basically just implemented this like he
had the best model for this in the
world. So you can use this for pose
estimation and whatnot, right?
So
uh here is
the third point.
15 seconds, guys.
Okay,
I'm going to end this poll shortly.
Hurry up and click otherwise. There she
goes.
Okay.
Anybody want to tell me the answer to
the questions?
True, true, true. Are you sure? Let's
see.
True, true, true. Indeed, you're right.
Right. To find the position using a CNN,
we need multiple output layers after the
final convolution. One to identify the
class, the other to predict the position
of the object. CNN's are invariant to
the position but not the orientation or
scale of the target pattern. To make
them invariant to a transform, transform
versions of every filter must be
included in the model for every
transform considered. Alternately uh you
can just use augmentation of the data
where you you include every variant of
the that you want robustness to uh in
the uh training data.
So there are many variants to this
model. You can have very deep networks
100 or more layers. This typically uses
a formalism called ResNet. Uh David,
yes, if you were pedantic, must own is
the wrong word. Okay. Uh if you want to
have many many layers in the network,
turns out training them is hard. So we
use a formalism calledism called ResNets
which you will encounter in your
homework. uh you have this thing called
depthwise convolutions which are another
variant of parameter shading which is
which can be used very often when you
want to train a very small model which
is just as almost as effective as a full
model here instead of using multiple
independent filters with independent
parameters we use a we use common layer
wise weights and combine the layers
differently for each filter. So what
exactly do I mean by this? Now think of
this in your standard convolution. If I
have a filter of this kind, the filter
has as many channels as the number of
input channels. Yes or no?
Right? What do you guys think? Okay. So
what really happens? One way of thinking
about it is that the first channel of
the filter convolves the first channel
of the input. The second channel of the
filter
convolves the second channel of the
input. Right? The third channel of the
filter convolves the
third channel of the input and so on.
Right?
And so the output of this is going to be
one channel each of which has been
obtained by convolving one of the
channels of the filter with the
corresponding input channel. Then all of
these are just summed up to get the
final output. This is the actual
appropriation we're performing. Right?
Yes or no?
Right? Make sense to everybody? The fact
that we just wrote big fat summations
doesn't change the fact that this is
what it we really do. Right? So if it
makes sense, give me thumbs up. I'd like
to wait to see 10 or 10 or 15 because
this formalism pops up.
Okay, I got my [laughter] 50.
So
if I have three filters, how much
computation am I performing? Each of
these filters has as many channels as
the input. Each channel of each filter
is convolving the corresponding input
channel. So if I had three filters and
if there were 10 input channels, I'm
actually performing 30 convolutions
which are being collapsed to three
output channels.
This making sense the numbers that I
just gave you. If I have three filters
and each of them has 10 channels, which
means there are 10 input channels. So
I'm computing 30 of these planes which
are being collapsed into three outputs.
That's a lot of computation because I'm
performing 30 convolutions, right? And
I'm computing a lot of intermediate
values.
So depthwise convolution
cheats a bit.
What it does it says instead of having
different each of these filters each
channel of every filter is different
right instead I'm going to have one
filter
and I convolve the input with this
filter the convolution is going to give
me as many
channels
as the number of channels in the filter
or the input in your traditional
convolution you just collapse these and
you get one output right Here instead of
collapsing them and getting one output I
do a weighted sum of these guys and by
changing the weights with which these
guys are added I get different output
channels.
That make sense to everybody?
All of you guys? Yes. No. Right. And so
with just one set of convolutions
I got multiple output channels. This was
what was called a depthwise convolution.
If this made sense, give me a thumbs up.
I have two thumbs ups, right?
Today I like the number 15. So yeah, 15.
Exactly. Exactly. Right. This has far
fewer parameters. It computes far fewer
intermediate values. So obviously it's
not going to be as good as a full
convolution, but it gets most of the way
there. And for a fraction of the compute
and a fraction of the memory and a
fraction of the number of parameters,
right? Does this make sense? If you
collapse the input channels, you're
going to get only one input channel,
right?
And so the number of parameters is going
to be one. If you collapse the input
channel, you're just left with
one of these planes for each output. So
the number of parameters is going to be
far fewer. It's a good good question,
Bruno. It's just that it's going to be
suboptimal, right? you don't have enough
flexibility with doing that because the
input is collapsed.
So conventional versus depthwise. In
conventional convolution, each of these
filters is going to give you an output
channel, right? And then they're all
summed up. In depth wise, these
filter channels give you different
output channels and you just sum them up
with different weights to get the
different output channels. And so the
number of parameters and the number of
computations and the number of
intermediate values are all going to be
far fewer. I have some arithmetic here.
Skip that. I think you guys got the
idea. So here is my final poll.
15 seconds, guys.
Five.
Okay, let me end this.
Did anybody notice this? Notice this
pictures on the top right.
Okay,
there's a code over there. I'll let you
figure out what the code was. I had one
on every poll. What are the answers?
>> False and true, right? filters and depth
wise convolutions convol all the input
channels simultaneously and sum the
result. No, they actually keep this
channel separately and then uh do the
weight or do a different weighted sum
for each output. They require far fewer
parameters and computation than regular
convolutions.
Right?
So depthwise convolutions because you're
not collapsing it and you're retaining
the depth of input channels they call it
depthwise convolutions. So to add to our
lessons, several variations of the basic
model exist to get obtain greater
parameter efficiency, better ability to
compute derivatives, etc. Right? This is
the last bullet.
What are the filters themselves learn?
Now again going back to our first second
lesson on convolutional networks, there
was a notion of a receptive field which
was the region of the input that each
filter saw. But they also it also refers
to the patterns that it detects. The
pattern in the input image that each
neuron sees is
you know it's receptive pattern
receptive field right the receptive
field for first layer neurons is simply
the arrangement of weights. For higher
layer neurons because the higher layer
neurons can can can respond to different
groups of different combinations of
their patterns. you actually need to use
back propagation to detect what the
neuron has fired for for and this is
going to be input specific and so
there's a process to it I won't get into
the details but here are what we find so
here as a CNN this these are CNN's that
were trained on uh different classes
this was and so when you analyze the CNN
and see what the receptive field was
what patterns the neurons ired for in
response to for each of these classes.
You find that the first layer p neurons
they all end up detecting these
patterns. What do these guys look like?
The patterns the receptive fields of the
first layer pattern neurons. What do
they look like? Edges.
Do they looks familiar to something we
saw earlier a few lectures ago?
Like what is
S cells? These end up looking much like
the kinds of patterns that mamalian the
mamleian vision system captures. That's
the magic. You put in all of this thing.
It's was kind of started off as a
mimicry of mamian vision. What? And
guess what? When you train the model,
the kinds of patterns it detects at the
lowest level indeed look like the kind
of patterns that our visual cortex seems
to respond to. That's magic, isn't it? I
don't know about you, right? And so, and
then look at what the higher level cells
get when they're looking at faces. The
higher level neurons, intermediate
neurons get all parts of faces. The
highest level neurons each fire for a
different kind of face in a different
slightly different position. Right? Uh
when you're looking at cars, the
intermediate neurons get parts of cars.
The highest level, they find cars in
different positions.
elephants. These find intermediate
neurons fire for parts of elephants. The
highest level neurons fire for full
elephants in different positions. Same
with chairs, right? And so what we are
finding is that you actually get this
very hierarchical buildup of patterns,
very satisfying, which is exactly the
kind of thing we even see in mamleian
vision and we hope to get and we indeed
do get it. Right?
There are lots of training issues,
standard convergence issues. The
solution is to use Adam or other
momentum style algorithms. Tricks like
batchnorm. You'll do those in your
homework. The number of parameters can
quickly become very large. So you'll get
insufficient training data to train the
model. Well, solution data augmentation.
What we do is that we modify our
training data to make fake training
instances. For this, for example, this
guy is some kind of a crazy cell. But if
I rotate it a bit to the right, it
remains exactly the same class. If I
flip it, it remains the same class. So
we modify the data through things like
rotation, translation, rescaling,
flipping, shearing a bit, stretching to
create different variants of the same
data instance which will have the same
class label. And these augmented data
are often used to expand your training
data.
CNN's are one of the most frequently
used formalisms today. used everywhere
not just for images they're used in
speech and audio processing and they're
even used in text processing amazingly
enough right so and if you actually go
to Andre Karpati's Stanford web page you
can get some very nice visual examples
so let's just spend a little time going
through the history the first really
viable CNN was Yan Leon's lanet and Yan
Leon's lanet this was it this was from I
think the original paper an image would
go in which was a 32 + 32 pixel image.
The first layer consisted of four 5 + 5
convolutional filters. So the first
layer would give you four maps. And
because these were 5 + 5, the result was
only 28 + 28. Remember the edges, you
lose things at the edges. Then he had a
max pooling layer which looked at 2 +2
windows and then had a stride of two. So
it shrank everything by a factor of two.
And that resulted resulted in five 14 +
maps four. Then he had 10 filters each
of size 5 + 5. And so as a result
because the filters are size 5 + 5
you're going to lose four rows and four
columns. And the outputs were uh what is
10 4 8 actually 12. The outputs were 12
10 + 10 maps. Then again max pooling
with a stride of two brought it down to
5 + 5. These were flattened and just put
through an NLP. This was a very simple
model and this basically revolutionized
uh machine learning. Right.
So this was linet
six is it? Maybe I got the numbers wrong
but all the details of the original lit
are on the slide.
Now let happened in the late 80s and
then things didn't move a lot for a very
long time till 2012
when
Hinton and co showed that com nets are
really good at image classification.
There's this classic challenge called
imageet the large scale visual
recognition challenge where the actual
data set had set had millions of images
in thousands of categories. The standard
evaluation used 1.2 million pictures,
thousands of categories. They were all
of these different categories,
[clears throat] right? Different
examples. And before CNN's were used,
the best models of the day,
I think, gave us something like a 25%
accuracy in top five accuracy in the
best case. And they couldn't get past
it. Then Hinton and co came up with this
thing called Alexnet.
It was so large for that day that it
wouldn't fit on one GPU. So they had to
fit it in two. And the picture wouldn't
fit in the paper. So they had to crop
the picture. This is the original
picture from the paper. The upper
portion of the picture is cropped. The
network contained 60 million parameters
and 650,000 neurons. Uh and they
introduced a few interesting uh
variants. This was the first time that
they actually used ReLU activations in a
convolutional network. Uh and so again
these are all the details of the
network. I'll skip the details
but the total parameters they had 650k
neurons 60 million parameters 630
million connections. This was considered
enormous for the day. And then during
testing they would take each test image
and crop it in many different ways in 10
different ways and classify each crop
and then vote over the lot
and some more training details. But
here's the bottom line. Overnight the
error that was 25%
went down from 25 to 18.2
with a single connet.
Even better, when they trained seven
different networks and voted over all
seven, the error went down to 15.4%.
So there was a 40% reduction in the
error overnight when they started using
connets. This was the uh aha mo moment
when people realized that neural
networks actually work and this changed
the world. Right? Of course, once we and
we found they found more things on their
network. They looked at the uh patterns
that the neurons at different layers
responded to. Sure enough, the first
layer neurons end up looking like S
cells. In mamleian vision, they detect
these oriented edges. Very beautiful.
Furthermore, they found that the network
learns very useful representations. So
first here are some classifications.
This was a might. It classifies it as a
might. It's a container ship. Classifies
it as a container ship. Motor scooter
leopard.
It does make make errors but the errors
are reasonable.
This is supposed to be a grill according
to uh imageet.
The model recognized it as a
convertible. Hey, it seems right. Right.
This is supposed to be a cherry. The
model thought it was a dalmation. I
think I I I kind of agree with the model
though more than the label in the data
set. Right? So this was supposed to be a
mushroom but the model recognized agaric
which is down here and so on. Right?
This is supposed to be a Madagascar cat.
It thought it was a squirrel monkey. It
looks like a squirrel monkey. So even
the errors were very reasonable. And
here was something more important that
really mattered. In the final layer of
the network just before classification
you get a feature that can be that is
used to that is put through the softmax
right they use that feature as a
representation for the input and
performed retrieval and so when they use
a feature derived from a picture of this
flower and they retrieve other images
from from the from the data set they
retrieve flowers when they use an
example of an elephant the other images
that they retrieve are elephants for a
ship. They're ships for this uh
Halloween lantern.
All the other images they retrieve were
also uh Halloween lantern lantern. So
they showed that the network actually
learns semantically meaningful
features of the data which is uh pretty
amazing right
of course once somebody jumps into the
fray others jump you know start
something off others jump into the fray
as well. So Zyler and Fergus trained a
small variant on Alex net and they
reduced the error from 15.4 to 14.8.
Then these guys the VGNET guys they ran
an insane number of experiments with uh
you know 140 million parameters which
was considered too large for the day and
brought the error down to 7.3%.
Then Google doesn't want to be left
behind. So they came up with this really
ugly model which they call inception. It
brought it down to 6.7% all within a
year, right? And then ResNet came in and
they chopped that error down to 3.5%.
And so here we are, right? Within one
year, we've gone for a couple of years,
we've gone from a 25% error to a 3.5%
error. Why ugly? It looks ugly to me. I
don't know about you guys, but this
looks hideous. Okay. Uh, so
[clears throat]
all right. And so ResNet is you're going
to encounter Resnet. So I I'll skip
that. Right? Then people come up came up
with denset. And then it became some
kind of a crazy competition where you
could literally go out for a cup of
coffee and come back and find an
improvement in the error rate. Was that
bad. Then eventually people you know
cooled down and then they moved on to
more interesting things. convolutional
neural networks had conquered the world
and of course the thousands of uh you
know papers hundreds of applications CNN
for speech recognition language
processing what have you and CNN for
your homework right I have some more
examples on the slides I skip that end
of the class at 7:49
did the lecture make sense
Give me a thumbs up if it did.
Can I wait for like 40 thumbs ups this
time because it's the end of the class?
>> Okay. All right, guys. Do you have any
questions? If I'll stop the recording.
Do you have any questions? Professor,
I